<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Other Stuff Exists</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/feeds/book.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/</id><updated>2015-07-05T10:35:22-04:00</updated><entry><title>Star Trek 8 by James Blish</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-8-by-james-blish.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-05T10:35:22-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-07-05:other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-8-by-james-blish.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few more months brings us to the final &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; book of the year: James Blish's &lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1dFZZvF"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 8&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, published in November 1972. This volume adapts "Spock's Brain", "The Enemy Within", "Catspaw", "Where No Man Has Gone Before", "Wolf in the Fold", and "For the World Is Hollow and I Have Touched the Sky".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1dFZZvF"&gt;&lt;img alt="Star Trek 8 cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/star-trek-8-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first story in this book is the execrable "Spock's Brain". Good news, though! If you've seen the episode, then you'll recall that they wire Spock's body up and drive him around like an RC car. None of that in the adaptation--the body remains safely in sickbay for the duration. Blish deserves a medal for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's still not a very good story, unfortunately. Although Blish reduced the story's stupidity substantially, he didn't do anything to improve its women-in-power-are-evil-and-incompetent message. If anything, he exacerbated that problem. Some choice quotes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The five male bodies, helplessly stretched at her feet, pleased the lady. When the girl Luma joined her, the spectacle pleased her, too.
[...]
Beside each woman knelt a man, sleek, well fed, docile as a eunuch. Occasionally a woman stroked a man as one pats a well-housebroken pet.
[...]
They &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; retardates, Kirk thought. Getting through to whatever gray matter existed in that beautiful head was going to be tough.
[...]
The women around her, infected by her panic, twittered like birds at the approach of a snake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, the thrust of the last two is that the women were helpless because the machinery cared for them too well. It's unfortunate, all the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, if you know &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt;, you can guess what happens. Kirk's solution to his present dilemma is to disable the miraculous, life-giving machinery and encourage the women to survive by trading sex for food. Really. McCoy and Scott explain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"[...] However, the aid parties have provided the ladies with a tool for procuring food, furs and fuel from the men."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Oh?" Kirk turned from one to the other. "Money?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"No, sir," Scott said. "Perfume."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"I'm not given to predictions, gentlemen, but I'll venture one now," Kirk told them. "The sexual conflict on Planet 7 will be a short one."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The Enemy Within" has a point, but I was never sure that it was a very good one. Kirk is split by a transporter accident into an exaggerated evil version and a uselessly indecisive 'nice' version. It is, apparently, the opinion of &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; that the strength to act decisively springs from the same source as violent, base urges and that we therefore need these darker impulses. And also transporters are magic. Anyway, the main interest of this one, as with "Turnabout Intruder", was in seeing Shatner playing a different kind of Kirk, so it's not as interesting on the page. Tolerable, but nothing to write home about. Yeoman Rand's "I don't want to get you into trouble. I wouldn't even have mentioned it if technician Fisher hadn't seen you, too, and..." is as disturbing and unfortunate here as it was on the screen. The fact that this passes without comment shows the age of the story, indeed. And need I even mention how stupid it is to have her providing this testimony &lt;em&gt;while Kirk is standing there protesting&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Catspaw" and "Wolf in the Fold" are both rather bad. The former has little else going for it than being set in a castle, of all things, which worked better on the screen. As for the latter: it features our heroes deciding that a small series of murders must have been committed by Jack the Ripper, who must have been some kind of alien that feeds on emotions. This theory is considered to be logical by almost everyone, and Jack the Ripper is taken as a serious suspect, even when placed up against &lt;em&gt;the woman-hating man who was found with the bloody murder weapon in his hands&lt;/em&gt;. Of course, that man was Scotty, so Jack the Ripper seems a more likely suspect to the readers, too. Naturally, the theory is correct, and said evil alien is conveniently on hand to be despatched by a combination of absurd computer handwaving and drugs followed by a one-way trip through the transporter. A deeply stupid story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Where No Man Has Gone Before" has a concept with potential. But it, like its television counterpart, fails to convince me. Gary Mitchell, granted enormous mental powers, succumbs to extreme megalomania and Kirk is forced to kill him. The most unbelievable part of this is that everyone simply acts as though this insanity is an absolutely normal and expected reaction to gaining a new ability. Mitchell, a day or two after learning that he can get a drink of water without standing up, decides that he wants to play god and possibly squash his former friends like bugs. Why? Because he's insane, obviously. But no one is particularly surprised by this. It mystifies me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"For the World Is Hollow and I Have Touched the Sky" is the best story in this volume. Like most &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt;, it doesn't fully explore its premises, but it's entertaining. It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; startling how quickly the characters can fall in love, though. Five minutes around any reasonably attractive alien woman is all it takes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1dFZZvF"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 8&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a thoroughly average entry in the series. Some bad stories and some good, and generally readable if not gripping.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="James Blish"></category><category term="Star Trek"></category><category term="novelization"></category><category term="science fiction"></category></entry><entry><title>Star Trek 7 by James Blish</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-7-by-james-blish.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-05T00:29:28-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-07-05:other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-7-by-james-blish.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Keeping up the pace, in July 1972 James Blish released his seventh volume of novelizations, &lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1dFpfSU"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In this volume are adapted "Who Mourns for Adonais?", "The Changeling", "The Paradise Syndrome", "Metamorphosis", "The Deadly Years", and "Elaan of Troyius".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1dFpfSU"&gt;&lt;img alt="Star Trek 7 cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/star-trek-7-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Who Mourns for Adonais?" reminds me once again how shockingly often Kirk's first response to a problem is to kill it. Apollo, jealous god that he is, was certainly being obstinate, but except for his severe reactions to Scotty's aggression, he wasn't really doing anything &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; objectionable. They were all more or less held hostage, sure, but Apollo seemed pretty reasonable, and if Kirk had been willing to try something other than shooting the ship's phasers to get out of the situation, they might have &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; made it through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not much to say about "The Changeling". It wasn't my favorite episode--frankly, I'd rather read &lt;em&gt;Star Trek: The Motion Picture&lt;/em&gt;. Well, that's coming up--the novelization was published in 1979.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The Paradise Syndrome" was an interesting episode, since we get a lot of passage of time, plus we see Kirk develop a relationship with Miramanee. He's in a habit of falling suddenly in love, of course, but I believe this is the very longest relationship we ever see Kirk engaged in. A nice change of pace. It is a shame that Miramanee's people are shown as not having advanced in many hundreds of years, though. Necessary, to let Kirk fit in where he did, but not exactly the most positive portrayal of Native Americans. I understand that in the original script Miramanee and the (unborn) child survive, but Blish's adaptation follows the episode as aired to its tragic (if very convenient) end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Metamorphosis" is in some ways a good story and in others a dreadful one. We meet Zefram Cochrane (am I the only one who is reminded of Trip from &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt;?), alive, young, and immortal (for the moment), plus a (temporarily) inscrutable alien energy being, and we get to see love conquer all. Very entertaining. On the other hand, we get to hear Kirk (bizarrely) proclaim "The ideas of male and female are universal constants, Cochrane. The Companion is definitely female." No, Kirk, it's some kind of alien energy being. That doesn't stop it from loving Cochrane, though. Even for the sixties, this seems an astonishingly absolute statement. The character of Hedford exists pretty much exclusively to be shrewish and then to give Cochrane a more acceptable body for his slavishly devoted alien lover. Not the best of &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt;. What I said regarding "Who Mourns for Adonais?" about Kirk first trying to kill any problem he encounters goes for this story, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The Deadly Years" was in some ways better in this adaptation than on television. It felt to me that in the episode, the actors were making something of a mockery of age. Without the overdone 'senile old man' performances from the main cast, it's easier to sympathize with Kirk's loss of control over his ship and, by extension, his life. It's still not great, but it has its high points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Elaan of Troyius&lt;/em&gt;... as progressive as &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; wanted to be, it took most every opportunity to get it wrong. As anti-slavery as Kirk has shown himself to be in, for example, "Who Mourns for Adonais?", he is here perfectly happy to serve as the enforcer to a woman's being property (never mind the political justification). He even says it himself: "My orders--and yours--say you &lt;em&gt;belong&lt;/em&gt; to that other man." And Kirk's only problem with the situation is that he would prefer if she belonged to &lt;em&gt;him&lt;/em&gt;, instead. And I need do no more than mention the awful 'taming the savage woman' plot to show just what is wrong with &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; part of the story. Elaan goes from fiercely independent (and just generally fierce) to utterly submissive in the space of a page or two, for no justifiable reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual, this volume has its good and its bad parts. I can't fault Blish--much--for the quality of the stories. I presume he wasn't entirely free to simply rewrite them as he saw fit, and at any rate that wasn't in his job description. &lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1dFpfSU"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 7&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; contains enough good to be worth reading, even if it doesn't deliver on the full potential of the stories.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="James Blish"></category><category term="Star Trek"></category><category term="science fiction"></category><category term="novelization"></category></entry><entry><title>Star Trek 6 by James Blish</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-6-by-james-blish.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-04T00:05:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-07-04:other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-6-by-james-blish.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Close on the heels of his previous book, James Blish published another entry in his series of &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; novelizations, &lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1FZNamK"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 6&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This one includes adaptations of "The Savage Curtain", "The Lights of Zetar", "The Apple", "By Any Other Name", "The Cloud Minders", and "The Mark of Gideon".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1FZNamK"&gt;&lt;img alt="Star Trek 6 cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/star-trek-6-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blish's introduction to this volume is amusing; he reprints a substantial selection from a letter he received from a real Captain Kirk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By an interesting coincidence I happen to be Captain [Pierre D.] Kirk. This being the case, the men of my last command built a rather elaborate "organization with an organization" based on the series. My jeep was slightly altered so that its registration numbers appeared as NCC-1701. Our weapons were referred to as phasers...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He goes on, recounting an interesting anecdote from his time in Vietnam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the stories: they're the usual fare, I'm afraid. "The Savage Curtain", if you'll recall, involves simulacra of Abraham Lincoln and Surak fighting alongside Kirk and Spock for the entertainment and edification of some inscrutable alien species. Here was a great chance for Blish to elaborate on Kirk's identification with and admiration of Lincoln, or to give us more insight into Vulcan culture. Alas, he only wrote a straight adaptation of the script, and reading about Abraham Lincoln engaging in a wrestling match isn't as entertaining as seeing it happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The Lights of Zetar" is simply not an interesting story. The most interesting thing about it is that it was co-written by Shari Lewis, famous puppeteer--and thus we learn that television writing is not her strong suit. It's all right; I still like Lamb Chop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The Apple", too, is as uninspiring as its counterpart on television. Here Blish might have considered in more detail whether Kirk really did right by essentially destroying a utopian society, but no. Best to rush back to the ship in time for the 'Spock looks like Satan' joke. A terrible pity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"By Any Other Name" was fairly amusing on television. The short story suffers without James Doohan's very entertaining performance as Scotty trying to get an alien drunk--and succeeding, but being too drunk himself to do anything about it. This story has another example of Kirk's predisposition to solving every problem with alien women by kissing them. "Oh. You are trying to seduce me," says the woman in question. "Go on then," she does not say, but that's how it happens anyway. Kirk really only has one diplomatic skill. It's fortunate he rarely has to negotiate with &lt;em&gt;men&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both "The Cloud Minders" and "The Mark of Gideon" were stories with, I feel, a great deal of potential, but neither was explored in any real depth, so each ends up being fairly forgettable. The former addresses class issues, and the latter some tangle of overpopulation, birth control, and suicide. Plenty of room to tell interesting stories, but instead they just rush from scene to scene without wasting any time contemplating the issues at hand. It's a shame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1FZNamK"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 6&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is another set of average adaptations of an average mix of episodes. If you particularly enjoyed "The Savage Curtain", it'd be worth a read, but that's really the only bright spot here. And to think, there are five more of these books! What horrors will the next volume unleash?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="James Blish"></category><category term="Star Trek"></category><category term="novelization"></category><category term="science fiction"></category></entry><entry><title>Star Trek 5 by James Blish</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-5-by-james-blish.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-03T21:35:42-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-07-03:other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-5-by-james-blish.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With 1972 came another entry in Blish's series of &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; adaptations, &lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1H4B4fQ"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This volume includes adaptations of seven episodes: "Whom Gods Destroy", "The Tholian Web", "Let That Be Your Last Battlefield", "This Side of Paradise", "Turnabout Intruder", "Requiem for Methuselah", an "The Way to Eden".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1H4B4fQ"&gt;&lt;img alt="Star Trek 5 cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/star-trek-5-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stories adapted in this volume are, I think, fairly average &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; fare. The adaptation of "Whom Gods Destroy" is the most interesting, but even it was better for being on screen. Meanwhile, most of the others are dull, and "Let That Be Your Last Battlefield" is positively tedious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several adaptations throughout this series suffer from a common flaw: certain episodes are really only interesting on account of being acted out. "Turnabout Intruder" has a rather weak plot (to say nothing of its unfortunately anti-feminist dimensions), but to the extent that it was entertaining, it was all down to Shatner's overacting as Dr. Lester. Blish's condensed prose captures none of that, while retaining the cringe-worthy story ("And most of all she wanted to murder the man who might have loved her--had her intense hatred of her own womanhood not made life with her impossible."--lovely.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above goes equally for "The Way to Eden", another very weak episode propped up (poorly) by songs, on which small support the book cannot rely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1H4B4fQ"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 5&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was saddled with several very unfortunate episodes, and it didn't make any more of them than the TV series did. If you've got this one, read "Whom Gods Destroy" and ignore the rest. If not, I wouldn't go out of my way to get it. Your time will be better spent elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="James Blish"></category><category term="Star Trek"></category><category term="science fiction"></category><category term="novelization"></category></entry><entry><title>The Making of Star Trek by Stephen E. Whitfield</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/the-making-of-star-trek-by-stephen-e-whitfield.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-03T22:45:19-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2015-07-03:other-stuff-exists/book/the-making-of-star-trek-by-stephen-e-whitfield.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In August, 1966, Stephen E. Whitfield, then in the employ of an advertising agency, was tasked with working to generate publicity for &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; toys. In consequence of his close contact with the &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; cast and crew, he became intimately familiar with the workings of the production, and pitched to Gene Roddenberry a book detailing the making of the show. With Roddenberry's approval, Whitfield began work on what was to be a thorough history of &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;, from its conception through the production of its first season: &lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1f7C7mf"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Making of Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1f7C7mf"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Making of Star Trek cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/making-of-star-trek-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whitfield's book was the first of its kind: a real behind-the-scenes look at the creation of a television show, including not only Whitfield's observations, but also interviews with Roddenberry and the actors, and original artifacts from the show's production, such as the 'series format' Roddenberry wrote to sell the show to the studio, and a variety of memos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned series format is perhaps the single feature of greatest historical interest, as it describes Roddenberry's initial vision for the show. In part:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;THE FORMAT&lt;/small&gt; is "Wagon Train to the Stars"--built around characters who travel to other worlds and meet the jeopardy and adventure which become our stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;THE TIME&lt;/small&gt; could be 1995 or even 2995--close enough to our times for our continuing cast to be people like us, but far enough into the future for galaxy travel to be fully established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;THE FAMILIAR LOCALE&lt;/small&gt; is their vessel--the U.S.S. &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt;, a naval cruiser-size spaceship. (In the initial draft of the format, the ship was the U.S.S. &lt;em&gt;Yorktown&lt;/em&gt;.) The vessel (a permanent set) includes bridge, control rooms, crew quarters and facilities, science labs and technical departments, plus passenger and cargo accommodations. These compartments contain the wide range of personalities, some becoming Guest Star roles for stories aboard ship or on the worlds we visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;THE LEAD ROLE&lt;/small&gt; is &lt;em&gt;Captain Robert T. April&lt;/em&gt;, mid-thirties, an unusually strong and colorful personality, the commander of the cruiser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;OTHER CAST REGULARS&lt;/small&gt; are a variety of excitingly different types: &lt;em&gt;"Number One"&lt;/em&gt;, a glacierlike, efficient female who serves as ship's Executive Officer; &lt;em&gt;José "Joe" Tyler&lt;/em&gt;, the brilliant but sometimes immature Navigator; &lt;em&gt;Mr. Spock&lt;/em&gt;, with a red-hued satanic look and surprisingly gentle manners; &lt;em&gt;Philip "Bones" Boyce&lt;/em&gt;, M. D., ship's doctor and worldly cynic; and uncomfortably lovely &lt;em&gt;J. M. Colt&lt;/em&gt;, the Captain's Yeoman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book features a great many more original documents from the show's production that will be similarly interesting to the devoted fan. It's well worth reading for those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of rather less interest (to me, at the least) are the minutiae of the show's production. In 1968, I suppose the work of making a television show was relatively unfamiliar to the average person. Today, I think this information has permeated the collective public consciousness, and at any rate the internet will offer (up-to-date!) details to anyone interested. Happily, these duller bits are in the minority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1f7C7mf"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Making of Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is an absolute treasure for the fan interested in &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt;'s history. I understand that many of these details have been republished, since, but Whitfield's book is the only source written even as the show was produced, and published contemporarily. It's well worth the time invested to read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those keeping track (just me, I'm sure), this book's proper place is between Blish's &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-2-by-james-blish.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-3-by-james-blish.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note on this review: I had believed that I'd reviewed this book months ago, when I finished reading it, but I cannot turn up that review, and I have since lost my notes on the book, so this is less thorough a review than I would wish. My apologies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="nonfiction"></category><category term="Star Trek"></category><category term="Stephen E. Whitfield"></category></entry><entry><title>Star Trek 4 by James Blish</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-4-by-james-blish.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-03T22:16:18-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-12-09:other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-4-by-james-blish.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Seventeen months after Blish's previous &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; book, &lt;em&gt;Spock Must Die!&lt;/em&gt;, was published, he finally put out a new volume of adaptations: &lt;em&gt;Star Trek 4&lt;/em&gt;. It was the only one published in 1971, but he then picked up the pace substantially, publishing four more in 1972 alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0553123114/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0553123114&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;linkId=GF3CSLNUKVQG32B4"&gt;&lt;img alt="Star Trek 4 cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/star-trek-4-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This volume includes adaptations of six episodes: "All Our Yesterdays", "The Devil in the Dark", "Journey to Babel", "The Menagerie", "The Enterprise Incident", and "A Piece of the Action".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the short stories are substantially similar to the episodes as aired, with the exception of "The Menagerie". That episode, if you recall, was a retooling of the pilot: Spock is court martialed for bringing Captain Pike back to Talos IV and presents the video from the pilot episode "The Cage" as evidence. Blish elected to omit the frame story and simply adapt the pilot episode itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several good stories, here, though not all of equal merit. I enjoyed the episode "A Piece of the Action", but I think that the short story falls flat--it was never much of a story, and most of its appeal was in the seeing. Ditto "All Our Yesterdays". The other four stories are quite entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really, the quality of the adaptations is good, but I find myself disappointed that they are so similar to the episodes. I suspect this is due to the book being written after &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; had finished airing, meaning that it was no longer necessary for Blish to rely on early draft scripts. This is good, if what you want are faithful adaptations of TV episodes, but it was the differences that made me interested in the books in the first place, so I think it's a shame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0553123114/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0553123114&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;linkId=GF3CSLNUKVQG32B4"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a worthwhile book, containing several entertaining stories. If any of those are your favorite episodes, I'd encourage you to give it a try, if only for the sake of nostalgia.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="James Blish"></category><category term="novelization"></category><category term="science fiction"></category><category term="Star Trek"></category></entry><entry><title>Spock Must Die! by James Blish</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/spock-must-die-by-james-blish.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-04T01:49:01-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-12-03:other-stuff-exists/book/spock-must-die-by-james-blish.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 1968, James Blish wrote in the introduction to &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-3-by-james-blish.html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that he would be writing an original &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; novel, the popularity of the television series warranting such an effort. By the time that book was published, in April 1969, &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; had already been cancelled, with only its final episode, "Turnabout Intruder", yet to air. Finally, in February 1970, Bantam published Blish's (sole) original &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; novel: &lt;em&gt;Spock Must Die!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001NCWD90/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B001NCWD90&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=VAGHK2IF2XMZNYNB"&gt;&lt;img alt="Spock Must Die! cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/spock-must-die-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt; is mapping out a region of space near the border of the Klingon Empire, a highly routine operation. Kirk comes upon McCoy and Scotty in the rec room, having a philosophical debate: is what comes out of the other end of the transporter the same person that went into it--does the soul make the jump? If not, McCoy says, then "every time we put a man through the transporter for the first time, we commit murder."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's no time to pursue this discussion further, for Spock interrupts to announce that the captain is needed on the bridge: the Klingons are at war with the Federation, and the &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt; is now behind enemy lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be impossible for the Klingons to break the peace treaty, but Organia (the home of the beings that instituted the treaty in "Errand of Mercy") seems to have been destroyed, so they are unhindered--and having great success. Unable to get into contact with Starfleet Command without giving themselves away, Kirk decides to head for Organia, a journey of several months, in hopes that the Organians have &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; been destroyed, and might be able to stop the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by his conversation with McCoy, Scotty invents a new kind of transporter which will make a temporary duplicate of a person and sent them away at great speeds and over enormous distances, with which he proposes to transport someone directly to Organia to investigate. Spock volunteers, and so the experiment begins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, things do not go as planned. After the attempted transport, they find &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; Spocks on the transporter pad, each claiming to be the original, and each apparently identical. The balance of the book concerns the efforts to distinguish which Spock is the duplicate (and must therefore be destroyed) and to reach Organia undetected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spock Must Die!&lt;/em&gt; is similar in style to Blish's adaptations, writ large. Blish liked to slip literary references into those short stories, and the novel takes it further, with references to works as varied as &lt;em&gt;Othello&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Narnia&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Finnegans Wake&lt;/em&gt; (the last of which forms a substantial plot point).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blish does take advantage of the freedom afforded by the increased length. The philosophical debate outlined above is not the only one in the novel, and if they are perhaps a bit overwrought, they are welcome reminders that science fiction can be about &lt;em&gt;ideas&lt;/em&gt;, and not merely action set in space. The general increase in detail is beneficial, as well; the adaptations often seem too brief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, I found the book's ending unsatisfying; the resolution of the plot is too straightforward. The &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt; set out to find a &lt;em&gt;deus ex machina&lt;/em&gt; to end the war, and they succeed in their search. There's no twist, no meaningful new complication. A technobabble explanation aside, there's little that couldn't have been predicted a dozen pages in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001NCWD90/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B001NCWD90&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=VAGHK2IF2XMZNYNB"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spock Must Die!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; isn't a bad book, and it's particularly interesting as a contrast to later &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; books. Blish's treatment of the characters is somewhat unique, and he certainly has no concern for maintaining the status quo. You could do worse than to spend a couple of hours reading this one.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="James Blish"></category><category term="Star Trek"></category><category term="science fiction"></category></entry><entry><title>Star Trek 3 by James Blish</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-3-by-james-blish.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-03T22:26:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-11-24:other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-3-by-james-blish.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another day, another collection of &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; novelizations. Today I'm looking at James Blish's &lt;em&gt;Star Trek 3&lt;/em&gt;, published in April 1969. It collects seven adaptations: "The Trouble with Tribbles", "The Last Gunfight" (an adaptation of "Spectre of the Gun"), "The Doomsday Machine", "Assignment: Earth", "Mirror, Mirror", "Friday's Child", and "Amok Time".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000HAZBGQ/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000HAZBGQ&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=YKS4TAMG7E23S65P"&gt;&lt;img alt="Star Trek 3 cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/star-trek-3-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't notice any substantial departures from the episodes in any of the stories except "Friday's Child", which treats the character of Eleen rather differently. "The Doomsday Machine" and "The Last Gunfight" have some small changes, as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is, like &lt;a href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-2-by-james-blish.html"&gt;its predecessor&lt;/a&gt;, fairly enjoyable. Although I've not found the series to be exceptional, it seems that contemporary readers were more impressed: in the introduction, James Blish describes some of his previous work (twenty-seven novels and short story collections, including a Hugo winner). Then:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I note these figures not to brag--well, not entirely, anyhow--but as background for one astonishing fact: I have received more mail about my two previous &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; books than I have about &lt;em&gt;all my other work put together&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He had been receiving letters "at an average rate of two a day ever since January 1967." Of note is that "most of [the letter writers] say that they have never read, or seen, any science fiction before &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;, or if they have, that they hadn't liked it." To fans looking for more information, he recommends &lt;em&gt;The Making of Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; by Stephen E. Whitfield. I'm reading that book, now, and it's fairly interesting (with some caveats--review forthcoming).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, at the end of the introduction, he very casually reveals his next project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks, too, to those who asked that I write an original &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; novel. Both the studio and Bantam agreed, somewhat to my surprise, that this was a good idea, so it's in the works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book in question, &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0553246348/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=0553246348&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=PVPDPR22H6RSQVPS"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spock Must Die!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, would be published in February 1970, nearly a year later, and Blish's next volume of adaptations would not be published until July 1971.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I admit that I'm really looking forward to &lt;em&gt;Spock Must Die!&lt;/em&gt; giving me a break from these adaptations. All the same, with adaptations of popular episodes like "Mirror, Mirror" and "Amok Time" (and even "The Trouble with Tribbles", if you're in a less serious mood), &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000HAZBGQ/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000HAZBGQ&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=YKS4TAMG7E23S65P"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a nice afternoon's diversion.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="James Blish"></category><category term="novelization"></category><category term="science fiction"></category><category term="Star Trek"></category></entry><entry><title>Star Trek 2 by James Blish</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-2-by-james-blish.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-03T22:33:19-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-11-21:other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-2-by-james-blish.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0553108115/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=0553108115&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=IEDQZ4FFDHFKNNRF"&gt;&lt;img alt="Star Trek 2 cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/star-trek-2-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Blish's novelizations of &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; episodes continue in &lt;em&gt;Star Trek 2&lt;/em&gt;, published in February 1968. This volume includes novelizations of "Arena", "A Taste of Armageddon", "Tomorrow is Yesterday", "Errand of Mercy", "Court Martial", "Operation--Annihilate!", "The City on the Edge of Forever", and "Space Seed".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each short story is typically quite similar to the episode being adapted, though there are some differences. Notably, the ending of "Operation--Annihilate!" is very different. In the episode, they expose Spock to a massive blast of electromagnetic radiation, including visible light, and believe that they have blinded him. Upon discovering that the visible light was unnecessary, they regret that they have &lt;em&gt;needlessly&lt;/em&gt; blinded him. In the end, though, he recovers, and they save the planet using the same procedure, on a larger scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the short story, the &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt; instead seeks out the central concentration of the mind-controlling creatures and destroys it with missiles, which leaves the creatures directionless and easily dealt with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the writing in this volume better than that in its predecessor, though I couldn't point at a definite reason why. It still suffers from the problem that the episodes on which the stories are based relied heavily on the visual element, and so are somewhat lacking as short stories. They don't generally have any big ideas behind them, and if they do they don't explore them very thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do think that some of the stories here have merit. Not much can be done for "Arena" or "Court Martial", but I can certainly see "A Taste of Armageddon" being worked into something more substantial and interesting, and of course that has already been done for "Space Seed" in Greg Cox's &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000FC0O22/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B000FC0O22&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=BWOUJ2F36227POEL"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eugenics Wars&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; series, not to mention &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B002I9Z8B2/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=B002I9Z8B2&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=LATKRVCNFFFAMU7V"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek II: The Wrath of Khan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not to be too negative, I did have a pleasant surprise when reading "Tomorrow is Yesterday". After their time-traveling adventure, Spock comments, "And so we have revised Omar." Upon Kirk's request for clarification, he specifies that he means "the verse about the moving finger." This refers to &lt;em&gt;The Rubáiyát of Omar Khayyám&lt;/em&gt;, as translated by Edward FitzGerald:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Moving Finger writes; and, having writ,
Moves on: nor all thy Piety nor Wit
Shall lure it back to cancel half a Line,
Nor all they Tears wash out a Word of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've only just read the &lt;em&gt;Rubáiyát&lt;/em&gt; about a year ago (highly recommended, incidentally), so seeing this reference by Spock is a treat. Sadly, I don't recall him being quite so literary in the episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given its general improvement over its predecessor, I can recommend &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0553108115/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=0553108115&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=IEDQZ4FFDHFKNNRF"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek 2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to fans looking for a quick read, or another perspective on the episodes, and the new ending to "Operation--Annihilate!" and the incorporation of content from Heinlein's original script in "The City on the Edge of Forever" provide a little added value.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="James Blish"></category><category term="novelization"></category><category term="science fiction"></category><category term="Star Trek"></category></entry><entry><title>Mission to Horatius by Mack Reynolds</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/mission-to-horatius-by-mack-reynolds.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-03T22:53:04-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-11-20:other-stuff-exists/book/mission-to-horatius-by-mack-reynolds.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've just written about James Blish's &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;, the first &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; book ever published, but that book contained only adaptations of television episodes. The first original &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; story published--and, indeed, the only such book published during the initial airing of &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;--is Mack Reynolds's &lt;em&gt;Mission to Horatius&lt;/em&gt;, published in 1968.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/067102812X/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=067102812X&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=OJLIDPXQHYX7S63M"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mission to Horatius cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/mission-to-horatius-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt; has been out on patrol for a long time, and just when they were heading for a much needed break, they are ordered to a distant star system--Horatius--from which a distress call has originated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horatius has three colonized planets: Neolithia, Mythra, and Bavarya. Neolithia was colonized by people who wanted a less technologically dependent way of life, and its inhabitants have only very primitive technology--not even iron. Mythra was colonized by people fleeing religious persecution, and is ruled by a small class of religious elites. Bavarya, the most recently settled, was colonized by political dissidents, and its leader is a militaristic man called &lt;em&gt;Nummer Ein&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt; is not welcomed by the inhabitants of any of the three planets, but they have a duty to determine who called for help, and render aid if they can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt; has troubles of its own. It has been far too long since the crew has been planetside, and Dr. McCoy fears an outbreak of space cafard, a deadly psychological condition caused by the extreme ennui of protracted space travel. If the crew of the &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt; don't get leave soon, they may tear themselves apart from the strain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mission to Horatius&lt;/em&gt; is a quick, easy read. With its A plot of the &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt; investigating a distress call, its B plot of McCoy's concerns about space cafard, and a good dose of comedy, it reads very like an episode of the show. Which is not to say that it's the most well-written possible book, of course. Kirk is rather cavalier in his response to the situation in which he finds himself, and his actions are not what one would expect of an ambassador of the Federation (as Kirk calls himself). He repeatedly ignores the wishes of the governments of the planets they're visiting, despite himself noting that he must not do that. He even says, "We shall see what our Bavaryan bullyboys have to offer," when it is Kirk himself who is acting the bully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While not flawless, &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/067102812X/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=067102812X&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=OJLIDPXQHYX7S63M"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mission to Horatius&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a suitably enjoyable read for young audiences, for which it was intended.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Mack Reynolds"></category><category term="Star Trek"></category><category term="science fiction"></category></entry><entry><title>Star Trek by James Blish</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-by-james-blish.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-03T22:39:28-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-11-19:other-stuff-exists/book/star-trek-by-james-blish.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've read a good number of &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; books, over the years. Since I came rather late to the &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; universe, I'm quite used to thinking of the expanded universe as a sprawling thing, composed of many books by a similarly vast number of authors. Of course, it wasn't always this way. Once, there were no &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; books at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, there was one: &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; by James Blish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1553056299/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=1553056299&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=LX4HAYTTNJHOP5KN"&gt;&lt;img alt="Star Trek cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/star-trek-1-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1553056299/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=1553056299&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20&amp;amp;amp;linkId=LX4HAYTTNJHOP5KN"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a collection of seven short story adaptations of television episodes, namely "Charlie's Law" (aired as "Charlie X"), "Dagger of the Mind", "The Unreal McCoy" (aired as "The Man Trap"), "Balance of Terror", "The Naked Time", "Miri", and "The Conscience of the King".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blish's adaptations were based on early draft scripts of the episodes, so the stories in this collection are not exactly the same as those that aired, though the differences tend to be minor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quality of the stories varies. For the most part, they are clearly uninspired adaptations of television scripts: lots of dialogue, limited description, and very little of anything else. They serve well enough as summaries of the episodes, but they're not particularly engaging, and I don't think they give enough detail for readers who haven't already seen the episodes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stories are inferior to the television episodes, too, in those cases where the acting is particularly noteworthy: Morgan Woodward's performance as Simon van Gelder in "Dagger of the Mind" and Arnold Moss's performance as Karidian in "The Conscience of the King" brought the characters to life in a way the lifeless dialogue in the short stories cannot match.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book does have one good point, however: the adaptation of "Balance of Terror" is substantially better than the other stories. Indeed, it's so different that I'd have guessed it was written by another author entirely. Where the other adaptations are soulless collections of dialogue and stage direction, "Balance of Terror" takes some time to consider the import of events and the relationships between the characters, and gives more detail than is strictly required to understand the events. This added flavor places it head and shoulders above the rest: it's a satisfying and entertaining short story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blish's book was apparently very popular. Published in January 1967, it was in its fifth printing by June of that year, and in its eighth printing by June 1968. My copy is from a 25th printing in February 1977 and claims "Over 8 million copies in print.", though that might possibly be including the later books in the series. At any rate, it was popular enough that the series was gathered into two different omnibus sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However interesting this book may be as a window into the past, I cannot recommend it. I don't regret the time spent reading it, but those simply interested in reading a work of science fiction should probably choose a different book.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="James Blish"></category><category term="novelization"></category><category term="science fiction"></category><category term="Star Trek"></category></entry><entry><title>Strange and Amazing Facts about Star Trek by Daniel Cohen</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/strange-and-amazing-facts-about-star-trek-by-daniel-cohen.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-04T02:01:43-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-03-25:other-stuff-exists/book/strange-and-amazing-facts-about-star-trek-by-daniel-cohen.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0671630148/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0671630148&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/strange-and-amazing-facts-about-star-trek-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cohen's book contains facts about &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;, but there's nothing strange or amazing therein. The facts are mostly in the form of very brief summaries of a few episodes or (similarly very brief) biographies of a few principal actors. Almost everything in the book will be known to anyone who bothered to watch the show ("When the series begins Kirk is in his mid-thirties, and holds the rank of captain with a starship command."), and the little that might not be is generally of little interest ("Another of Bill Shatner's current enthusiasms is the horses that he rides and breeds on his southern California ranch.").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting part of this book is the chapter on the fans, which talks about the letter-writing campaign to save &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; from cancellation, fanzines, conventions, and the broader impact of &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; in the years since its cancellation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book concludes with a 22-question trivia quiz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stephen E. Whitfield's &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B003UR0V2C/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B003UR0V2C&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Making of Star Trek&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is by far this book's superior, and even Wikipedia is more informative.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Daniel Cohen"></category><category term="nonfiction"></category><category term="Star Trek"></category></entry><entry><title>The Entropy Effect</title><link href="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/book/the-entropy-effect.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-04T01:56:30-04:00</updated><author><name>Tracy Poff</name></author><id>tag:sopoforic.github.io,2014-03-23:other-stuff-exists/book/the-entropy-effect.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A little break from all these picture books seems to be in order, so let's go with something completely different: &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1451607539/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=1451607539&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Entropy Effect&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Vonda N. McIntyre, which is #2 in the Pocket Books line of &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; novels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1451607539/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=1451607539&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20"&gt;&lt;img alt="The Entropy Effect cover" src="https://sopoforic.github.io/other-stuff-exists/images/entropy-effect-cover.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Enterprise&lt;/em&gt; has been in orbit of a singularity for six weeks, Mr. Spock making careful observations of this unusual phenomenon, when they are called away to Aleph Prime by an ultimate override command--to be used only in the most dire of situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They arrive to find no great emergency at all. Instead, they're asked to transport a criminal a short distance to a rehabilitation facility. Captain Kirk would have angrily refused, but Spock asks him to accede to this request. It seems that the criminal in question is a scientist of Spock's acquaintance, and there's something fishy about the situation. Spock's investigation uncovers a threat to the entire universe, which he must handle covertly, if he can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Entropy Effect&lt;/em&gt; focuses on a few characters only: Spock, McCoy, Kirk, and Sulu, plus Mandala Flynn and Hunter, characters original to the novel. The bulk of the novel follows Spock as he deals with the situation, but it takes time to give us some insight into the others, as well. Importantly, in &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; history, it is in this novel that Sulu is given his name, Hikaru (which wouldn't be officially confirmed until a decade later, in &lt;em&gt;The Undiscovered Country&lt;/em&gt;), and promised a promotion to lieutenant commander.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original characters are the high point of the novel. Flynn and the security officers under her command are each interesting: Flynn's desire to prove herself is admirable; Jenniver's difficulties fitting in inspire sympathy; Neon's unusual language (consisting only of nouns) and Snnanagfashtalli's loyalty to Jenniver each merit a mention, as well. Hunter, Kirk's past love, is of little import to the plot, but she does add some needed variety. She has a child, and is part of a nontraditional family arrangement--it's good to show that humans, too, are diverse. There are as many ways to live as there are people on the Earth, and space travel doesn't do anything to simplify that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it odd that each of the characters I identified as being of particular interest is female? Early &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; is certainly a story of men, and this novel, for all its focus on Spock, does somewhat counterbalance that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Entropy Effect&lt;/em&gt;'s plot eventually revolves around time travel, and it's handled fairly well, in a &lt;em&gt;Star Trek&lt;/em&gt; sort of way. It's shown to be difficult and far from consequence-free, and there's a bit of suspense as we wonder how (though--let's be honest--not &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt;) Spock will manage his task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All told, &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1451607539/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=1451607539&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;tag=othstuexi-20"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Entropy Effect&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is an average book: not great, but fun enough to read once. I understand that several of the original characters show up in other &lt;em&gt;Trek&lt;/em&gt; novels; I'll look forward to reading those, some day.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Star Trek"></category><category term="science fiction"></category><category term="Vonda N. McIntyre"></category><category term="time travel"></category></entry></feed>